I’ve been told that we sand martins talk too much.
That we have no sense of privacy and that our loud constant chatter is a nuisance to other creatures.
But what they don’t know is: our conversations are never pointless. Our voice can save our lives.
My friends Atsu and Etse were usually chosen as vigils. They were brothers, quite small for their age, who had been selected for their powerful, piercing call.
They used to perch on top of a large baobab, which offered a 360° view over the forest. From there they were on the look-out, as we had many predators, and none of them scared us so much as the hawks.
We lived in a constant state of emergency.
My mom had forbidden my brothers and I to venture too far from the colony.
So we stayed there, apparently lazing and chatting on the riverbanks, while really, we were just waiting for the call.
All it took was a high-pitched shrill, a piercing siren and in a few seconds, all birds retreated inside our bunkered nest.
It was a complex network of tunnels carved inside the clay of the banks by generations of sand martins.
From the openings, we could see the hawks circling around our heads. They were just biding their time.
They knew that, come summer, our food supplies would be depleted, forcing us to move further and further.
They knew that the summer rain would make us slower and more vulnerable.
Yes, a 14g bird travelling 5000 kilometres must be mad. But staying would be even madder.
On the day of departure, eighty of us joined the flock. We gathered on power lines not far from our nest.
Three rows of sand martins, an army of young birds ready to conquer Europe.
For once, none of us talked. We just prayed, in silence.
And then, as one body, we all opened our wings and took over the blue open sky.